and making today possible. Thank you to
everyone in the Commonwealth who voted,
who volunteered,
um who stood up for fair representation.
Because of you, we have held back a
Republican power grab and leveled the
playing field in the fight for the
majority in the people's house. Last
night's results are what happens when
voters decide, and it's as simple as
that. Contrast that to House Republicans
who have at every possible opportunity
ignored the people that they are
supposed to serve. Last year, they hid
from the public while they shoved their
big ugly bill through that decimated
healthcare, raised costs, and took food
off of people's tables, all because
Donald Trump demanded it.
They stayed on vacation during the
longest government shutdown in history
while Democrats were fighting for
affordable healthcare.
And instead of listening to their local
businesses or the struggling families in
their districts pleading with them to
stop Donald Trump's reckless reckless
tariffs,
they just rubber-stamped them.
So, when Donald Trump called up and
said, "Give me five more seats in
Texas,"
it is sadly no surprise that they all
just said, "Yes, sir."
And that's fundamentally what's been
behind the Republican effort to rig the
midterms, of subservience to Donald
Trump while they ignore their
constituents back home.
But, we're seeing the American people
fight back. Voters from California to
Virginia and everywhere in between won't
let Republicans cheat their way into
holding on to power.
Um we've always said that the public
hates the Republican scheme to rig the
midterms, and when given the
opportunity, they would hold Republicans
accountable for their attack on fair
representation.
And last night, the voters of Virginia
rejected the Republican power grab and
helped put us on the path to House
Democrats taking back the majority.
Listening to the American people and
fighting for them should not be a novel
concept, yet for Republicans, they're
either incapable or indifferent to it.
Their refusal to fight for the people is
a defining contrast, and because
Democrats are listening to the people,
we are winning.
And our work is not yet done. The
ultimate referendum will take place at
the ballot box this November, and we're
confident that voters will hold
Republicans accountable for their cruel,
cost-spiking,
and corrupt agenda, and power Democrats
to victory in the midterms when we take
back the House majority.
This has been a critical time. We are
using every tool to continue to fight
back and stand up for the American
people, and the person who has been
leading us, and as I said before,
tirelessly, has been our incredible
leader, Hakeem Jeffries. I'm going to
turn it over to him.
>> Good morning, everyone. Thank you so
much to Susan [clears throat] DelBene,
our field general, who is doing an
extraordinary job leading the DCCC in
our efforts to make sure that we take
back the House in November.
House Democrats will continue to fight
one battle after another on behalf
of the American people.
We're battling them on the economy,
battling them on tariffs, battling them
on health care, battling them on
nutritional assistance, battling them on
ICE funding, battling them on Donald
Trump's reckless and costly war of
choice, and battling them on their
gerrymandering scheme.
Last night was a big victory for the
people of Virginia, a big victory
for America, and a big victory for
democracy. Donald Trump and Republicans
launched this gerrymandering war.
And we've made clear as Democrats that
we're going to finish it
on behalf of the American people. We
will not let Donald Trump
rig
the midterm elections
by gerrymandering maps all across the
country without a forceful
Democratic response.
That is what you saw in Virginia. That
is what you will see in Florida, and
that is what has taken place all across
the country.
Prop 50
in California.
Forcing them into a dummy mander
in Texas.
Picking up a seat in Utah.
Stopping them in New Hampshire. Stopping
them in Indiana. Stopping them in
Kansas. Stopping them in Nebraska.
Pushing them back
in Ohio.
And winning
a big victory
for the American people
in Virginia.
These Republican extremists
thought that we were going to step back.
They had us confused.
We were never going to step back.
We're going to continue to fight back
all the way through November 3rd
when Democrats will take back control of
the House of Representatives.
So we can drive down the high cost of
living, fix our broken health care
system, clean up corruption, get ice
under control, stop this reckless and
costly war of choice, end this national
nightmare in America, and continue our
country's march toward a more perfect
union. I want to thank Governor
Spanberger, thank Speaker Don Scott,
thank the General Assembly, thank the
Virginia Congressional Delegation, and
thank President Barack Obama, Attorney
General Eric Holder, and everyone who
was involved in this extraordinary
effort
to get this done in Virginia
as part of our
unyielding commitment
to stop the MAGA power grab
wherever it is taking place across this
country.
It's now my honor to yield
to the whip,
my good friend, my classmate, this
extraordinary leader, Katherine Clark.
>> Thank you so much.
Thank you so much, Mr. Leader. We are so
grateful for you, for your vision, for
your fight, and for helping have this
victory. And to Susan DelBene,
for her courage and strength as she
marches towards victory in November,
giving us the resources and the vision
of how we get this done.
So, it's a funny thing about a GOP
agenda that inflicts higher prices,
corruption, and war. It makes people
angry, and it inflicts economic pain.
But, instead of choosing to work for
Americans, the Republicans in the House
have decided to rig our elections. They
tried to cling to power by choosing
their voters. And this started
in North Carolina in the 24 elections,
where the three seats that they
eliminated cost us the majority.
But, they went on, instead of taking
that majority and putting it to use for
the good of the American people, it has
been an agenda of costs, cruelty, and
chaos.
Democrats have taken a different route.
We think the American people should
decide the future of their democracy. We
think they should decide who controls
the people's house, not the politicians.
And that's why we're putting
redistricting on the ballot, not making
backroom deals that are forced on
voters. And that's why we are winning.
The American people deserve better than
they're getting.
They deserve better than illegal tariffs
and healthcare cuts and secret police
causing chaos and murdering Americans in
the streets.
That's why Republicans are losing this
redistricting fight that they started
from California to Utah to now Virginia.
And it's why Democrats are going to win
in November.
And I am also on my list of those that
we are grateful to include the chairman
of our caucus, Pete Aguilar, who helped
us lead the efforts in California to
meet Republicans and bring us to victory
in that redistricting effort and was
absolutely critical in the results we
saw in Virginia. With that, I yield to
you, Pete.
>> Thank you, Whip Clark and to Susan
DelBene and Leader Jeffries. Truly,
without their efforts here leaning in,
this would not have happened. But it's
very clear. The American people have
spoken.
They are not going to stand by and let
Donald Trump and House Republicans rig
our elections so that we have 2 more
years of making life harder and more
expensive for working families. In
Virginia and California and Utah and in
states around the country, Americans
have made their voices heard and they
have fought back against Republican
attempts to silence them. For more than
a year, the American people have watched
as Republicans have ripped away
healthcare, driven up costs, prioritized
billionaires over their lives. But,
rather than change their policies to
actually improve the lives of people
around our country, Republicans and
Donald Trump have doubled down
working to steal the next election
to support their own efforts. Democrats
won't let that happen. I was privileged
to play a role in our efforts in
Proposition 50 in California to directly
counter Trump and the Texas scheme that
he engineered. And in the fall,
Californians made it clear
that Republicans had violated that trust
that night. And And Virginians made it
clear last night.
And they said clearly, "Enough is
enough." While Republicans take their
cues from Donald Trump
drawing maps in bathrooms and in the
middle of the night without input of
voters, Democrats in these examples that
we have talked about took that fight to
the American people. And at the ballot
box
members
constituents in these states had the
opportunity to push back against Donald
Trump. And the people decided. Democrats
have the momentum, the candidates, and
the American people on our side. We will
fight and we will win the House this
November. Republicans have started this
fight, but Democrats, and more
importantly, the American people are the
ones who will finish it.
>> Yield back to the leader.
>> Thank you, Pete. And let me join
Katherine in thanking you uh
and members of the California
delegation, Zoe Lofgren, who did an
amazing job
in connection with that unified effort
to win Prop 50 decisively at the
beginning of this fight. And as Pete
indicated and Katherine and Susan, we're
in this fight until we win this fight on
behalf of the American people.
Questions?
>> If Democrats do win back the House next
year,
will you advance a bill to ban
gerrymandering and advance independent
districting or is this
recognition of a new era when every
state can try to draw maps based on
political parties?
>> We've continued uh to stand behind our
prior efforts to establish one national
standard
that would prohibit mid-decade partisan
gerrymandering all across the country.
But, what we're not going to do
is unilaterally disarm.
Apparently, that's what Donald Trump
believed
that we would do. That's what James
Blair
believed
that we would do. They had us confused
in terms of the moment that we're in
and the need to push back consistently
with the fierce urgency of now.
>> Going back to that moment uh when James
Blair was talking about Texas, there was
a lot of talk talk about how risky this
is that it would look like you guys were
hypocritical by now embracing a response
by mid-decade re-gerrymander. So, can
you take like go back to that moment and
why you decided to move forward on this?
>> The stakes are incredibly high and it's
the American people
who should be the ones to decide who
serves in the majority, not Donald Trump
and his MAGA extremists.
They launched this gerrymandering war
because they were trying to rig the
midterm elections
and prevent the people from being able
to decide
who actually controls the majority. And
the reason why they've launched this
gerrymandering war is because
Republicans under Donald Trump have been
a complete and total failure.
They failed on everything, everywhere.
Most significantly on the economy.
And that have gotten us into this
reckless
war of choice.
I want to yield to Susan and Katherine
to respond to this, but
from the very beginning
in our conversations with Gavin Newsom
the Democrats in the Texas legislature
who made the brave decision
to go on quorum break so they could
shine a spotlight
on Donald Trump's gerrymandering scheme
nationally
as opposed to
Texas Republicans being allowed to
simply get away with it in the dead of
night.
But we also decided that as we were
going to respond
we were going to respond in a manner
consistent with our values. Yes, we were
going to win this fight.
But it's also important to note
our response has been forceful
temporary
as a direct reaction to what MAGA
extremists have done and at all times
approved by the voters.
That's the big difference between how
we've approached this effort and
Republicans who are going into state
legislatures in the dead of night
passing maps and then being afraid
to present those maps
to the people in those states.
Right now in Missouri
we have collected enough signatures
to take the Missouri gerrymander before
the people in November
for an up or down vote
as to whether that map should take
effect after
the 2026 election. And Republicans are
fighting us in court.
And so we don't want to hear any pearl
clutching from these people
on the other side of the aisle.
We take our case to the voters.
They don't.
And if they're on the right side of this
fight,
why are they pushing back in Missouri?
Just allow the map to go forward.
The current map
to go forward, and then the voters can
decide in Missouri pursuant to the
Missouri Constitution
as to whether it should be enacted.
Republicans are fighting us
right now because they're afraid
of their own voters.
But we're going to keep the pressure on
them
at all times.
After I'm through, Susan.
>> I just want to add the reason they
started down this path is they know the
American people um have turned against
the Republican agenda. And so if you
think you're winning with voters, they
support what you're doing, um the
legislation you passed, the actions
taken by the White House, then why would
you go about trying to rig the system?
They're rigging the system because they
know they're losing. And instead of
listening to the American people,
they've decided the only way they can
win is to try to redistrict and change
the rules to favor them. And it is as
the leader said, they won't go to the
people.
They don't take the vote to the people
in Missouri. They're doing everything
possible to try to prevent the people
from having a say. In Florida, the
people have been clear. They passed a
law to prevent mid-cycle redistricting.
And
they're not going to the people to ask
them if they want to change that. Um
they're trying to look at redistricting
there as well without talking to the
people of Florida. That's what
Republicans are doing across the board,
and I think it's very clear people are
tired of the Republican agenda. We've
seen in special elections Democrats are
running ahead across the country. Um and
we have opportunities even in place like
Texas now because people are so
tired of what they see from Republicans
to pick up seats. So, we are going to
continue to fight all across the country
and the American people are with us.
>> Yeah, we just briefly re-emphasize what
the leader just said. They are operating
from a place of fear.
Because they fear their own voters.
Because they chose an agenda that drove
up prices, that has corruption at its
heart, and that has created chaos in
American communities.
Um, as
what they were going to do. And when the
American people are telling them that
they are not making it, that over 60% of
American families are unable to meet the
basic needs,
their response isn't we've got to
correct course and start working for
them, live up to our promises of
reducing costs, of releasing the Epstein
files, and no new wars, they're going
along with an agenda that gives up on
all of that. And so when they are trying
to win an election on broken promises,
this is what they came up with as the
only path forward.
The choices have always been there for
them. They choose Donald Trump over the
American people.
And now they are choosing a power grab
over putting this before voters. And so
at every turn, we are going to stand
firm and together
with what the American people are asking
from us.
To see us, get us relief in housing
prices, groceries, utility bills,
restore our health care and help it
overhaul this system so I can afford
health care where and when I need it.
And get a government
that is working for me, the taxpayer,
and is not
uh
working for the benefit of a president
and his family.
This is what the American people are
desperate for. And after their
redistricting that they did behind
closed doors in Texas, what did we see
in the primary? A Democratic turnout
that was well over Republican that
hasn't happened in decades. It was
presidential-level
turnout. And last night in Virginia, we
saw the same turnout of a gubernatorial
race.
When not a single candidate on the
ballot, but the idea that our elections
should be fair, and they should be
secure, and that our agenda should be
focused on the American people. That's
why it won. That's why we'll win in
November.
>> Perfect. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. The
Supreme Court released a decision today
on whether or not we're losing our
voting rights case. Are you confident
that when the decision does drop that it
may be too late for it to have an effect
on these maps, or are you all taking
contingencies for when the decision
drops? How may it impact any of the
games that you may play?
>> The right thing for the Supreme Court to
do is to uphold Section 2 of the Voting
Rights Act. This is a historic,
enduring, bipartisan
piece of legislation. The Voting Rights
Act is the most important civil rights
legislation ever enacted in the history
of the country, and it's designed to
protect free and fair elections.
Just 2 years ago,
Justice Roberts and Justice Kavanaugh
upheld Section 2 of the Voting Rights
Act. And for the life of me, I can't
figure out why they would do anything
different in this instance.
Now, I know that some of the far-right
justices
who are operating in the pocket of the
Republican Party
are trying to do everything possible
to give MAGA extremists an electoral
advantage and we're just not going to
let it happen.
Whenever the Supreme Court decision
comes down, hopefully
a majority of the justices do the right
thing. But whatever the circumstances
are,
we are committed to ensuring that
there's going to be a free and fair
election in November. And when that
happens, Democrats will take back
control of the House of Representatives.
>> How would Democrats respond if the
Virginia non-partisan Supreme Court does
ultimately strike down the new map and
find the referendum illegal?
>> The law is with us
in Virginia.
The facts are with us
in Virginia. And the people are with us
in Virginia. There's no basis in law or
fact for the Virginia Supreme Court
under the
constitution that exists,
particularly in the aftermath of a
people-approved referendum,
to do anything other than to allow it to
move forward.
>> Looking at the record of the state
Supreme Court, they have shown a
willingness to greenlight already
gerrymandered maps in spite of their
Fair Districts Amendment, how confident
are you that you will prevail in court
should the Republican plan act in that
way?
>> We're
We know that
you know, the governor has talked about
ignoring the will of the people. We're
going to continue to fight back. And we
also know that we have opportunities
across Florida to pick up seats and we
will continue to do that. People again
are tired of what they see the
Republican priorities are not the
American people, but basically doing
Donald Trump's bidding. And you've seen
even in state legislative seats in
Florida, just huge swings even more
recently including that legislative seat
with Mar-a-Lago in it. A huge swing
because people want folks who are going
to stand up for them. So, I think we
have opportunities in Florida
and absolutely we're going to fight back
every way that we can to make sure that
their voices are heard.
>> Our message to Florida Republicans is f
around and find out.
If they go down the road of a DeSantis
dummymander,
the Florida Republicans are going to
find themselves in the same situation as
Texas Republicans
who are on the run right now and under
no circumstances are Texas Republicans
picking up five seats. They'll be
fortunate if they get two or three.
While in California,
we are going to get all five. The
Republicans are dummymandering their way
into the minority before a single vote
is cast because they started this war
and we're going to finish it.
The electoral tide is turning in
Florida.
As Chairwoman Del Bene illustrated, we
won the Miami mayor's race in December
for the first time in almost 30 years
by 20 points.
And now Eileen Higgins is mayor
in a city that's 75% Latino
including Cuban Americans and Venezuelan
Americans amongst some of the more
conservative
members of the Latino community in the
nation.
But the city of Miami for the first time
in three decades broke heavily in our
direction.
We flipped the seat in Mar-a-Lago of all
places
when Donald Trump endorsed the
Republican candidate and Republicans
went all in.
And we also won a seat in that same
special election last month
in
Central Texas
in the Tampa Bay
area.
The signs are there, which is why
there are many
Republicans
within the congressional delegation who
have already publicly said in Florida
to their governor and to the White
House, it would be a mistake to go into
Florida and do a DeSantis dummy mandate.
We agree. But go ahead
and make our day.
We are all in
in Florida.
And it's Republicans who are putting a
target on the backs of their own members
politically
at this moment in time.
Last question.
>> Uh
thank you, Leader. If Florida does go
ahead, where do Democrats What other
states do Democrats look to to counter
the maps?
>> We are in an era
of maximum
warfare.
Everywhere, all the time.
And we're going to keep the pressure
on Republicans in every single state in
the Union
to ensure at the end of the day
that there is a fair
national map
because we believe that it's the people
who should decide who's in the majority
in the next Congress, not Donald Trump
and MAGA extremists.
Thank you, all.
>> Thank you.
Yeah.
>> I got to do
>> I want to get
Oh, okay.
>> Thanks, man.
>> Hey, you made it.
>> Oh, really?
Thanks for making this.
>> [music]
[music]